Guide to the Thomas M. Balliet Papers MC 22
New York University Archives
Thomas M. Balliet Papers
1890-1948
MC 22
New York University Archives
2.5 linear feet (5 manuscript boxes)
The papers of Thomas M. Balliet consist of correspondence, manuscripts, lecture notes, newspaper clippings, photographs, and scrapbooks. These materials contain information on his career as Superintendent of Public Schools in Massachusetts and his appointment as Dean of the School of Pedagogy at New York University.
Biography of Thomas M. Balliet
Thomas Balliet was born March 1, 1852. He attended Franklin and Marshall College, receiving his A.B. in 1875 and Ph.D. in 1887. Balliet acted as Superintendent of Public Schools of Springfield, Massachusetts, from 1887 to 1904. In 1904 he was appointed as a professor in the New York University School of Education and Dean of the School of Pedagogy. He retired in 1919. Balliet died February 18, 1942, at the age of 90.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, lecture notes, newspaper clippings, photographs, and scrapbooks. These materials contain information on Balliet's career as Superintendent of Public Schools in Springfield, Massachusetts, as well as his service as Dean of the School of Pedagogy at New York University.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged into four series:
I. General Correspondence and Biographical Information
II. Published and Unpublished Works
III. Lectures
IV. Scrapbooks
Separated Materials note
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research without restrictions.
Balliet, Elizabeth; Loomis, Milton E.; MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1840-1918; New York University. School of Education .; Thomas M. Balliet, (Thomas Minard), 1852-1942; Clippings.; Manuscripts.; Notes.; Photographs.; Public Schools. Massachusetts. Springfield.; Scrapbooks.; Universities and Colleges. Administration.
- Series I: General Correspondence and Biographical Information, 1890-1948
  - Biographical Sketch, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to Balliet as Superintendent of Schools, Springfield, Massachusetts, 1890-1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence re Balliet's appointment as Dean, School of Pedagogy, 1900-1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence to Mrs. Elizabeth Balliet re Biological sketches of Thomas M. Balliet, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Mrs. Elizabth Balliet re death of Thomas M. Balliet, 1942-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Published and Unpublished Works, 1896-1928
  - "Details in HIstory", undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Infidel Books", undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "The Influence of the Present Methods of Graduate Instruction on the Teaching in Secondary Schools." The School Review, Volume XVI, Number 4, Apr, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "The Instincts and Education." American Physical Education Review, Volume VIII, Number 1, Mar, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Introduction of Sex Education into Public Schools." The American Social Hygiene Assocation, Number 571, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Language.", undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "The Moral Value of Genuine Intellectual Work.", undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "The Motive and Method in Modern Lanuages.", undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Philosophy of Education.", undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Secret Organizations.", undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Self-Culture.", undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Some New Phases of Modern Educational Thought." The Association Review. Volume 11, Number 2, Apr, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Spelling." The Public Schools of Springfield, Massachusetts., 1896 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "The Vocational Motive in Education." American Education. Volume XVIII, Number 5, Jan, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Why Study a Modern Foreign Language?", undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, A-H., undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, L-S., undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, unalphabetized., undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series III: Lectures, 1907-1908
  - General Methods, Oct 2, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Watch Experiment (missing), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Faintness of Concepts, Oct 16, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Demonstrable Idealism, Oct 23, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Compariosn, Oct 30, 1907, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Goal of Instruction is Generalization, Nov 6, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - A Discussion of Chapters 5 and 6, McMurray's "Method of the Recitation", Nov 13, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Advantages and Disadvantages of the Dogmatic Lecture Method of the Text-Book, Nov 20, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Absorption and Reflection, Nov 27, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Crowded Curriculum, Dec 4, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Summary of the Five Formal Steps, Dec 11, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Types, Coordination, and The Broad or the Narrow Curriculum?, Dec 18, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - The Language Group of Studies, Jan 18, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Fundamental Principles of Teaching in the Language Group, Jan 22, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Assocation with Reference to Language Study and Music, Jan 29, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Decimals--Language Study, Feb 5, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The Laws of Habit, Feb 19, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Art Studies, Mar 4, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The Relation of Science and art, Mar 11, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The Emotions as Related to Art and Religion, Mar 18, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks, undated
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and photographs of various schools (primarily in Massachusetts)., undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and photographs of various schools (primarily in Massachusetts)., undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and photographs of various schools (primarily in Massachusetts)., undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and photographs of various schools (primarily in Massachusetts)., undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and photographs of various schools (primarily in Massachusetts)., undated (Box 5, Folder 2)